Leon Kroll
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Leon Kroll papers
1905-1974
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kroll, Leon
6.0 linear feet
The papers of realist painter, muralist, and art instructor Leon Kroll date from 1905 to 1974 and measure 6.0 linear feet. The collection documents Kroll's painting career, teaching, and active participation in numerous art organizations. Over one-half of the collection is correspondence with artists, schools, galleries, museums, patrons, arts organizations, and others. Also found are scattered biographical material, writings and notes, legal and financial records, exhibition catalogs, clippings, other printed material, photographs of Kroll and colleagues, loose drawings and nine sketchbooks.
Provenance
Leon Kroll donated a portion of his papers in 1968. His widow, Genevieve Kroll, donated the rest of the papers in 1976.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2009 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Photographs and printed reproductions of artwork as well as select financial documents have not been scanned.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Leon Kroll (1884-1974) of New York, N.Y., was a painter.
Leon Kroll was born in New York City in 1884. As a teenager he attended classes at the Art Students League and studied painting with John Henry Twachtman. In the early 1900s he began taking classes at the National Academy of Design, where he won student prizes, and had his first major exhibition in 1906. In 1908 he won a scholarship to study art in Paris and attended the Académie Julian, studying at the atelier of Jean-Paul Laurens. Through he practiced realism, Kroll was also influenced by French impressionist painters, specifically Paul Cézanne. While in Paris he also met Genevieve (Viette) Domec. They married later in 1923 and had one daughter, Marie-Claude.
Upon his return to New York in 1910, Kroll had a one man show of his Paris work at the National Academy where he received critical acclaim. The next year he began teaching at the National Academy of Design. During his career, he also taught at the Maryland Institute, Art Institute of Chicago, the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, and was a guest instructor and lecturer at several other schools.
Kroll was part of a circle of New York artists that included several members of "The Eight", and he was especially close with Robert Henri, William Glackens, George Bellows, and Eugene Speicher. During his time in Europe he also became friends with Marc Chagall and Robert and Sonia Delaunay. He exhibited at the Armory Show in 1913 and during the next few decades won numerous major national and international prizes in painting, including first prize at the 1936 Carnegie International Exhibition. He had his first retrospective exhibition at the Worcester Art Museum in 1937. Kroll was especially known for his paintings of female nudes, but also painted New York City street scenes, New England landscapes, and portraits. Beginning in the late 1930s he was commissioned to paint murals at public buildings including, among others, the U. S. Department of Justice Building, the war memorial in Worcester, Massachusetts, and the auditorium at Johns Hopkins University.
Throughout his career Kroll was a very active member of professional arts organizations. He was an Associate and later a Academician at the National Academy of Design, and his memberships included the New Society of Artists; American Society of Painters, Sculptors, and Gravers; Artists Equity Association; Four Arts Aid Association; and the National Institute of Arts and Letters among others. He also served as a board officer for many of these organizations. Kroll was active in the federal arts programs from the 1930s to the 1950s and close friends with Edward Bruce, director of the U.S. Treasury Department's Section for Fine Arts.
Kroll maintained a studio in New York City and spent summers at his home and studio at Folly Cove, Gloucester, Massachusetts. Leon Kroll died in 1974 at the age of 89.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of realist painter, muralist, and art instructor Leon Kroll date from 1905 to 1974 and measure 6.0 linear feet. The collection documents Kroll's painting career, teaching, and active participation in numerous art organizations. Over one-half of the collection is correspondence with artists, schools, galleries, museums, patrons, arts organizations, and others. Also found are scattered biographical material, writings and notes, legal and financial records, exhibition catalogs, clippings, other printed material, photographs of Kroll and colleagues, loose drawings, and nine sketchbooks.
Biographical material contains chronologies, biographical essays, awards, price lists, interview transcripts, and a file about the Committee on Government and Art. More than one-half of the collection consists of Kroll's personal and professional correspondence with artists such as Gifford Beal, George Biddle, Isabel Bishop, Barry Faulkner, William Glackens, Robert Henri, Paul Manship, Hobart Nichols, Eugene Speicher, Maurice Stern, Esther Williams, and many others. Additional correspondence is with art critics, curators, dealers, students, patrons, schools, museums, and numerous arts organizations. There is also extensive correspondence with arts administrators regarding government art projects, especially his friend and fellow artist Edward Bruce, Director of the U. S. Treasury Department's Section for Fine Arts.
Writings and notes by Leon Kroll including autobiographical essays, drafts of lectures and speeches, lists, and other scattered notes. Also found is a small amount of writings by others, including an essay by Julia Langsam describing her experience as an artist's model for Kroll. Legal and financial records include contracts, loan agreement, art sales receipts, and several ledgers recording consignments and monthly receipts and expenditures. One ledger specifically documents financial transactions for his mural commissions for the Justice Department and the Worcester War Memorial.
Printed material contains numerous news clippings about Kroll and his work and includes several articles written by Kroll. Also found are exhibition announcements and catalogs for Kroll's solo exhibitions, material about the Worcester War memorial, and miscellaneous printed items.
Photographs include one of Kroll with his family, Kroll in his studio and working on murals, and several of him with other artists as jurors for art exhibitions. Artists depicted include Isabel Bishop, Reginal Marsh, John Sloan, Raphael Soyer, Eugene Speicher, and others. Also found are photographs of Edward Bruce, as well as photographs of exhibitions, artwork by Leon Kroll, and artwork by others. All of the original artwork in this collection is by Leon Kroll and includes loose drawings and nine sketchbooks containing drawings of landscapes, figures, portraits, and animals.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1906-1969 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1905-1973 (Box 1-4; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1932-1972 (Box 4-5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Legal and Financial Records, 1921-1974 (Box 5; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1924-1972 (Box 5-6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1900s-1960s (Box 6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1911-circa 1950s (Box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Economic aspects; Art patronage; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Art and state; Artists' models; Artists' studios--Photographs; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketches; Sketchbooks; Writings
Names:
Beal, Gifford, 1879-1956; Biddle, George, 1885-; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-; Bruce, Edward, 1879-1943; Faulkner, Barry, 1881-1966; Glackens, William J., 1870-1938; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Langsam, Julie; Manship, Paul, 1885-1966; Nichols, Hobart, 1869-1962; Speicher, Eugene E. (Eugene Edward); Sterne, Maurice, 1878-1957; Williams, Esther, 1907-1969
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1906-1969, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Biographical materials include autobiographical essays and chronologies compiled and updated by Kroll. The essays list schools he attended, prizes and honors, museums he is represented in, organization affiliations, etc. Also found are lists of paints and supplies found on his palette and lists of artwork and prices. Award certificates document the numerous honors he received from the National Academy of Design during his time as a student and during his early career. There are two interview transcripts, including one interview done for Columbia University in which he discusses his childhood and education in detail. This series also contains a file Kroll kept on the Committee on Government and Art which includes meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, and press releases, and other miscellaneous documents and records.
  Items within each folder are arranged in chronological order. The bulk of this series has been scanned; business and calling cards have not been scanned.
  - Biographical Summaries and Chronologies, circa 1932-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biography from "The Index of Twentieth Century Artists," 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Who's Who Biographies, 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Palette used at the present time by Leon Kroll" (List of items on palette), circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Artwork and Price Lists, circa 1940s-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Award Certificates, 1906-1908, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcript by Columbia University, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Radio Interview Transcript, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Government and Art Documents, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Visa Applications, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eulogy for Cornelius Kroll, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diagram of Kroll Property, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Map of Folly Point, Gloucester, Massachusetts, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Business and Calling Cards, circa 1930s-1960s, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1905-1973, Series 2:; (Box 1-4; 3.6 linear feet)
  Correspondence is the largest series within the collection and contains both Kroll's personal and professional correspondence, the bulk of which dates from 1930 to 1970. There is correspondence with many fellow New York and European artists, including members of the social realist and ashcan schools of painting and artists he met in his travels and participation in national and international art organizations and committees. There is also correspondence with students and publishers, requests for him to teach, lecture, or write articles, and business correspondence reagarding exhibitions, sales, donations, and commissions. There is very little family correspondence. A small amount of correspondence is in French.
  Artists that Kroll corresponded with nclude John Taylor Arms, Gifford Beal, George Bellows, Edwin Blashfield, George Biddle, Isabel Bishop, Marc Chagall, Arthur Covey, Randall Davey, Sonia Delaunay, Edwin Dickinson, Barry Faulkner, Ernest Fiene, Joseph Floch, William Glackens, Ellen Day Hale, Samuel Halpert, Robert Henri, Joseph Hirsch, Robert and Edward Hopper, Berthe Koch, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Richard Lahey, Paul Manship, Ezio Martinelli, William McKillop, Gari Melchers, Hobart Nichols, Henry Schnakenberg, John Sloan, Raphael Soyer, Eugene Speicher, Maurice Sterne, Stuyvesant Van Veen, Hutton Webster, Esther Williams, Hamilton Wolf, and Andrew Wyeth among many others.
  Kroll also corresponded with many art historians and critics, curators, and gallery owners, such as Arthur Byne, Alfred Churchill, Frank Rehn, and Louis Stern, and several art patrons and collectors such as J. S. Carpenter, Etta Cone, Aldus Higgins, Julius Lempert, and Carl Weeks.
  A large amount of the correspondence found here is Leon Kroll's professional correspondence with arts organizations, clubs, and committees in which he participated. This includes the American Society of Painters, Sculptors, and Gravers; Artists Equity Association; Municipal Art Committee of New York; National Academy of Design; and the National Institute of Arts and Letters, among many others. These files may contain copies of letters between other members, press releases, printed material, meeting minutes, or memos he sent to members. Also found is correspondence with arts administrators regarding federal government art projects and funding, including Edward Bruce, Forbes Watson, and Edward Rowan.
  In general, letters are filed alphabetically by person or corporate name. Names with five or more letters are filed in their own folders, and the remainder of correspondence is filed in miscellaneous files. Selected correspondents whose names do not appear in headings are indicated in a note following the folder heading. Some correspondence with individuals may also be filed according to the name of the organization with which they were associated. Where they exist, Kroll's outgoing letters are interfiled with incoming letters.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Abels, Alexander, 1939-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ACA Gallery, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Adler, Elmer, 1936-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Albert, Louis, 1949-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Allied Publications, Inc., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1936-1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1932-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Artist, 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Artists' Congress, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Artists Group, 1938-1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Artists Professional League, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1923-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - American-French War Relief, Inc., 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Magazine of Art, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American Society of Painters, Sculptors, and Gravers, 1920-1939, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Amherst College, 1939-1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - John Taylor Arms, 1935-1953 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Art Association of Newport, 1934-1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1919-1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Art Students League of New York, 1934-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1947-1961, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Artists for Victory, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Associated American Artists, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Aa-An, 1930-1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Ar-Av, 1928-1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1929-1938 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Banta, R. E. (Dick), 1952, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Beal, Gifford and Maud, 1938-1957 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bellows, George and Emma, 1913-1928 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bender, Albert, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Benepe, Robert S., 1932-1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Bicket, Kay, 1955, 1957, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Biddle, George, 1933-1968 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Bishop, Isabel, 1942-1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Blow, Richard (Dick) and Katherine, 1956-1959, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Bocour, 1936-1963 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Borden Publishing Co., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Borie, Charles, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Boston Art Club, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Briarcliff Junior College, 1935-1956 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Bruce, Edward (Ned) and Peggy, 1928-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
  - Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1924-1938 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Bushell, Adolph and Carole, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Byne, Arthur and Mildred, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Ba-Bi, 1930-1973 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    (Includes letters from Peggy Bacon, Hugo Ballin, Maurice Becker, and Thomas Hart Benton)
  - Bl-Bo, 1927-1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    (Includes letters from Edwin Blashfield and Louis Bouche)
  - Br-By, 1919, 1932-1972 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    (Includes letters from Alex Brook and Charles Burchfield)
  - Carnegie Institute (Homer Saint-Gaudens), 1925-1969, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 65-66)
  - Carpenter, J. S. (Sandy) and Florence (See also Des Moines Association of Fine Arts), 1924-1941, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 67-68)
  - Carson, Pirie, Scott and Company, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Central Hanover Bank and Trust Company, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Chemical Bank and Trust Company, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Childe Hassam Fund, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Churchill, Alfred, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - City of Chicago, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1925-1948 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Cohen, M. H., 1925-1935 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Colby College, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - College Art Association, 1931-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - College of William and Mary, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Columbia University, 1938-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cone, Etta, 1930-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cone, Sydney and Isabel, 1946-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Constance, Jane, 1939-1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art (C. Powell Minnigerode), 1930-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Covey, Arthur and Lois, 1925-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Crisp, Arthur, 1956-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ca-Ce, 1925-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ch-Cl, 1925-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    (Includes letters from Marc Chagall)
  - Co-Cy, 1924-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    (Includes letters from Alphaeus Cole)
  - Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, 1938, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Davey, Randall, 1915-1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Davidson, Lloyd, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dayton Art Institute, 1924-1943, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Delano, William A., 1938-1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Department of Justice, 1937-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Depauw University, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Des Moines Association of Fine Arts (See also Carpenter, J. S. and Florence), 1925-1932 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Detroit Institute of Art, 1919-1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Domec, Claude and M., 1929-circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dyson, Katherine (Kitty), 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Da-De, 1916-1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    (Includes letters from Andrew Dasburg, Robert and Sonia Delaunay, and Julius Delbos)
  - Di-Dy, 1931-1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    (Includes letters from Edwin Dickinson, Olin Dows, and Marcel Duchamp)
  - Edward Bruce Fund, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Edward Macdowell Association, Inc., 1937-1943, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ellis, Rhoda Winter, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Erdmann, Hayden Davidson, 1947-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - E, 1919-1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    (Includes letters from Philip Evergood)
  - Faulkner, Barry, 1951-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Fiene, Ernest, 1952-1965 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Finch College, 1935-1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fine Arts Foundation, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Fine Arts Gallery, City of San Diego, 1935-1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Fitchburg Art Museum, 1930, 1957-1966 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Floch, Joseph, 1909-1910, circa 1950s-1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ford Foundation, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Four Arts Aid Association, 1945-1953 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Fa-Fi, 1934-1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Fl-Fr, 1925-1966 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    (Includes letters from John Folinsbee and Juliana Force)
  - Gatterdam, Pascal M., 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Giles, Howard, 1923-1925, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Glackens, Ira, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Glackens, William and Edith, 1927-1940s (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Gonzalez, Xavier, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1932-1960 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Guggenheimer, Richard, 1936-1948 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Guillaume, Jules, 1925-1940, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Ga-Go, 1934-1963 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    (Includes letters from Grace Gemberling and Lloyd Goodrich)
  - Gr-Gz, 1930-1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    (Includes letters from Marion Greenwood, Chaim Gross, and Bob Gwathmey)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Halpert, Samuel, 1916-1930 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Harrison, Preston, 1916-1937 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Hartford, Huntington, 1952, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Henri, Robert and Marjorie, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Hessel, Grace (Mrs. Sidney), 1929-1930s (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Higgins, Aldus and May, 1933-1948 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Hirsch, Joseph, 1947-1962 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Hopkinson, Charles, 1947-1950s (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Horton, Henrietta, 1934-1935, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Ha, 1935-1969 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    (Includes letters from Lilian W. Hale)
  - He-Hy, 1931-1972 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    (Includes letters from Edward Hopper)
  - International Association of Plastic Arts, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Ismay, Diane, circa 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - John Herron Art Institute, 1936-1954 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1931-1938 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Joseph Paolillo Gallery, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - I-J, 1931-1960 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    (Includes letters from Sidney Janis and Edward Alden Jewell)
  - Kander, Allen and Mrs., 1956-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Koch, Berthe (Jane), 1933-1961, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Kogan, Nathan, 1952-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Kroll, Cornelius (Neil) and Grace, 1925-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kroll, Lenore, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Kroll, Marie-Claude, 1940s-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Kroll, Philip and Gwen, 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kroll, Viette, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kupfer, Frank, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - K, 1925-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    (Includes letters from James Kerr and Yasuo Kuniyoshi)
  - Lahey, Richard, 1929-1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Langsam, Walter and Julia, 1920-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lelarge, Henri, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lewis, Mary, 1936-1937, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Lempert, Julius, 1923-1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Library of Congress, 1922, 1941, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Life Magazine, 1938-1948 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lyke, Dr. Hyatt, 1931-1930s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - La-Le, 1916-1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Li-Ly, 1931-1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    (Includes letters from Jonas Lie, Georg Lober, and George Luks)
  - Maine Coast Artists, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Maison Nationale De Retraite Des Peintres, Sculpteurs Et Graveurs, 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Manship, Paul and Elizabeth, 1931-1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Martinelli, Ezio, 1934-1958 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Maryland Institute of Art, 1923-1946 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Matthias, Blanche, circa 1950s-1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - McKillop, William and Madge, 1924-1938 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Mechau, Frank, 1932-1948 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1925-1963 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Milch Galleries, 1925-1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Mills College, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Milwaukee Art Institute, 1934-1948 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Modarelli, James E., 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Montclair Art Museum, 1927-1969 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Morgan, Charles, 1961-1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Municipal Art Committee, New York, 1933-1939 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1937-1961 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ma, 1923-1967 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Mc-Mi, 1920-1972 (Box 3, Folder 41)